Guide to the Secular Yiddish Schools in North America Collection M0732
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Series 1. Yiddish school files
  - Grant, Lisa. Informational Material. History, Philosophy, Curriculum of Yiddish Schools., Accession no. 1997-055 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    Academic paper written at Jewish Theological Seminary, 1996, English, "A History of the Yiddish Schools Between the World Wars." Includes letter to G. Fishman.
  - Maymudes, August. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish. IWO. Wire-bound children's Yiddish elementary textbook mayn yidish bukh, missing cover. Also hard cover, D. Tarant, mayn yidish bukh, NY 1948., Accession no. 1997-056 (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Maymudes, August. Informational Materials: History, Philosophy and Curriculum of the Yiddish Schools. "Curriculum for the Jewish Secular School," prepared by teachers of the Los Angeles kindershules, 1962 (IWO-based). 73 pages. [1 of 2], Accession no. 1997-056; 1 vol. (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Maymudes, August. Informational Materials: History, Philosophy and Curriculum of the Yiddish Schools. "Curriculum for the Jewish Secular School," prepared by teachers of the Los Angeles kindershules, 1962 (IWO-based). 73 pages. [2 of 2], Accession no. 1997-056; 1 vol. (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Maymudes, August. Holiday Materials. Sholem Educational Institute, Los Angeles. "Chanukah Handbook." n/d. Benjamin Efron, "The Story of Purim;" "The Story of Passover," 1952. Sholem Community Organization, "Hagada shel Peysakh: Sholem Family Hagada for a Secular celebration of Pesakh," 1992. Hershl Hartman, "The Jewish New Year Festival: A Guide for the Rest of Us." 1992., Accession no. 1997-056 (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - Maymudes, August. Student Notebooks. IWO. Major Yiddish writers on cover of 3 blank notebooks., Accession no. 1997-056 (Box 23, Folder 14)
  - Maymudes, August. Miscellaneous. Poster, World Union of Jewish Students, 1971-72; Accession no. 1997-056 (Box 23, Folder 15)
  - Maymudes, August. Personal Memoirs., Accession no. 1997-056 (Box 23, Folder 16)
  - Fifer, Donald. Souvenir Journals. "shul zhurnal," Sholem Aleichem andandx0023;15, Brooklyn, NY. June 1936, June 1942. "yorbukh," Sholem Aleichem andandx0023;15, Brooklyn, NY. June 1943, June 1944, June 1965, June 1966, June 1967. Yiddish and English., Accession no. 1997-262 (Box 23, Folder 17)
  - Fifer, Donald. Souvenir Journals. "shul zhurnal," Sholem Aleichem andandx0023;35, Long Island City, NY. June 1957, June 1958, June 1959, June 1960, June 1961, June 1962, June 1965. Also "di shtim," Sholem Aleichem mitlshul, NY, 1948. Yiddish and English., Accession no. 1997-262 (Box 23, Folder 18)
  - Fifer, Donald. Yiddish Camp Materials. "Reactions of Second Generation American Jews to Problems of Jewish Living. A Study of Former Campers and Staff Members of Camp Boiberik." By Leibush Lehrer. 1961. English., Accession no. 1997-262 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Katz, Eli. Souvenir Journal IWO. tsentrale mitlshul, New York. July 1944. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-263 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Katz, Eli. Student Writings, Published and Unpublished. "Yungvarg," New York, April 1941. IWO. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-263 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Katz, Eli. Holiday Materials. Passover. IWO. History of Passover in Hitler's time (Shirley Kaplan and Miriam Shwartz), and poem by Eli Katz. By students. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-263 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Reivich, Elizabeth. Souvenir Journal. IWO. Philadelphia, PA. May, 1931. Collection of children's writings in honor of the 4th Spring Concert of the Jewish Children's Shuln. Yiddish. Accompanied by explanatory letter to Gella S. Fishman., Accession no. 1997-264 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Cymerman, Hadasa. Souvenir Journals. AR/WC West Bronx Shul andandx0023;7. New York, 1944. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-265 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Cymerman, Hadasa. Informational Material: History, Philosophy, Curriculum of Yiddish Schools. Farband. New York. Feb., 1965. Published by "lerer-rat un shuln-komitet." Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-265 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Cymerman, Hadasa. Holiday Materials. Passover, Purim, Hanukkah, Lag B'Omer, Mother's Day. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-265 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Cymerman, Hadasa. Pedagogical Materials: Israel. Undated. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-265 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Cymerman, Hadasa. School and Affiliated-Organization Newsletters and Bulletins. AR/WC. New York, 1957 and 1961. English., Accession no. 1997-265 (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Cymerman, Hadasa. Personal Memoirs, Published and Unpublished. Published in "seminarist," journal of "yidishe lerers seminar," New York, 1952. Yiddish. Also letter to Gella Fishman, May 1995. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-265 (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Cymerman, Hadasa. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Literature. Published in "Point of View," Jan. 1965. English., Accession no. 1997-265 (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - Cymerman, Hadasa. Tributes. 1982. Two notes from a student. English., Accession no. 1997-265 (Box 24, Folder 13)
  - Cymerman, Hadasa. Photographs. Graduating class of A. Liessin Folkshul (Farband), 1967. Photocopy. Also H. Cymerman with class, about 1980, on a Lag B'Omer outing., Accession no. 1997-265 (Box 24, Folder 14)
  - Cymerman, Hadasa. Affiliated Organizations: Documents. Program of 18th Annual Jerusalem Banner Award, given by Jewish National Fund, Feb. 1970. English. Also program of commencement exercises for Herzliah Hebrew Teachers Institute/Jewish Teacher's Seminary and People's University. June 1968. English, Hebrew and Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-265 (Box 24, Folder 15)
  - Cymerman, Hadasa. Pedagogical Materials: Holocaust., Accession no. 1997-265 (Box 24, Folder 16)
    Photocopy of photograph on cover of "kinder-tsaytung" (AR/WC. Jan. 1943, to be used for teaching about the Holocaust in Eastern Europe. Yiddish.
  - Goodman, Saul (donated by son Eli Goodman). Souvenir Journals. AR/WC West Bronx school andandx0023;7, New York, 1944. Yiddish. Also 5 journals "SAFI News" published by Sholem Aleichem Folk Institute, New York. Apr. 1969, Mar/Apr. 1970, Nov./Dec. 1971, Jan./Feb. 1972, Sept./Oct. 1972. English and Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-266 (Box 24, Folder 17)
  - Goodman, Saul (donated by son Eli Goodman). Curriculum Materials for Teachers. AR/WC., Accession no. 1997-266 (Box 24, Folder 18)
    Teacher's lesson plan notebook, prepared by Sorke Goodman, 1949-50. Yiddish and English.
  - Goodman, Saul (donated by son Eli Goodman). Informational Material: History, Philosophy, Curriculum of Yiddish Schools. Articles re Jewish Secularism in various journals. Yiddish and English., Accession no. 1997-266 (Box 24, Folder 19)
  - Goodman, Saul (donated by son Eli Goodman). Informational Material: History, Philosophy, Curriculum of Yiddish Schools. Articles re Jewish Secularism in various journals. Yiddish and English., Accession no. 1997-266 (Box 24, Folder 20)
  - Goodman, Saul (donated by son Eli Goodman). Holiday Materials. Rosh Hashonah. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-266 (Box 24, Folder 21)
  - Roth, Chane. Souvenir Journals. Sholem Aleichem Folkshul andandx0023;13, in honor of 10th Anniversary, July 1933, Brooklyn, NY. In honor of 17th Anniversary, June 1940. In honor of 20th Anniversary, June 1943. Sholem Aleichem Mitlshul, New York, di shtim, 1937. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-267 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Erenberg, Shirley. Photographs. IWO. Philip Balkin Shul, City Terrace, Los Angeles, 1958. One photocopy and one original., Accession no. 1997-269 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Erenberg, Shirley. Diplomas, Report Cards, Graduation Announcements and Certificates. IWO. Diploma, Westside Kindershul, June 1964. Photocopy. Report card, 1955. Original., Accession no. 1997-269 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Erenberg, Shirley. Archival Collections of Other Institutions. Letter to Ms. Erenberg from Skirball Museum, 1988.; Accession no. 1997-269 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Burstein, Esther. Photographs. Sholem Aleichem andandx0023;15, Brooklyn, NY., 1940s.; Accession no. 1997-270 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Burstein, Esther. Poetry About Secular Yiddish Schools. Sholem Aleichem. Photocopy of handwritten poem "tsu a fraynt" with typed version., Late1930s?.; Accession no. 1997-270 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Levine, Merke. Souvenir Journals. IWO. Jewish Cultural School of Nassau, NY., June 1967; June 1969; June 1970; Accession no. 1997-271 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    Originals, English.
  - Levine, Merke. Souvenir Journals. IWO. Jewish Cultural School of Nassau, NY., June 1971; June 1972; June 1975; Accession no. 1997-271 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Levine, Merke. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Language. Curriculum Materials for Teachers. IWO. Notebook of curricular materials. Yiddish., No date.; Accession no. 1997-271 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - Krystal, Shloyme. Estate of Chana Krystal. Pedagogical Materials: Jewish History. Teacher's informational sheets prepared by Chana Krystal and others. Birth of Christianity, Jews in America, Jews in Palestine. English. der yidisher yishuv in erets yisroyl, mitsraym un bovl. der yidisher yishuv in shpanye. der vidergeburt fun yisroyl. di tseshpartung fun di yidishe melukhe. der durkhfal fun der reform bavegung in europe. moyshe hess. yidn in amerike. Chana Krystal, "der limud geshikhte." No date. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - Krystal, Shloyme. Estate of Chana Krystal. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Language. Y. Levin, der onfanger leynbukh, zekster teyl. Hebrew Publishing Co.: New York, 1938. Yiddish. Letter chart with instructions for cursive writing., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 25, Folder 11)
  - Krystal, Shloyme. Estate of Chana Krystal. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Language. Y. Mark. arbets bukh far yidish in mitlshul, bukh 1. Educational Dept. Workmen's Circle: New York, 1949. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - Krystal, Shloyme. Estate of Chana Krystal. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Language. Coloring book. No author, part of mol un dertseyl, illus. Tsirl G. Waletzsky. Bildungs-komitet fun arbeter ring. No date. Yiddish/English. Alphabet sheets, published by Workmen's Circle, 1956. Grammar, composition and loshn-koydesh worksheets prepared by Chana Krystal. Yiddish and transliterated., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 25, Folder 13)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Language. A. Bergman, yidish arbetsbukh far der mitlshul. heft 2. Natsionale shul un kultur komisiye: New York, n.d. Journal Yiddish Lingo, (Rodale Press, Allentown PA, Jan.-Feb. 1970, 1:1); Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Administrative/Organizational Materials. AR/WC. Various documents., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Affiliated Organizations: Documents. Badge from AR/WC conference; leaflet about Jewish Currents; Jewish Current Events newsletter. Report by Chana Krystal to Bund, no date. List from National Conference on Soviet Jewry - pen pal program., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Pedagogical Materials: Bible. A.M. Fogel, "The Prophets." No publisher: no city, 1960. English. Notebook handwritten by Chana Krystal; notes on teaching of Bible subjects. Hebrew., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Curriculum Materials for Teachers. AR/WC curriculum, no date. Yiddish. "Outline of Studies for the Second Year of the Sholem Aleichem Sunday School." Feb. 1971. English. Outline for history, Yiddish and literature. 1965-66. New York. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Examinations: Elementary and High School. Yiddish language, history. English and Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Examinations: Elementary and High School. Yiddish language, history, holidays, Bible, Yiddish literature, social issues [1 of 2], 1960 - 1969; Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Examinations: Elementary and High School. Yiddish language, history, holidays, Bible, Yiddish literature, social issues [2 of 2], 1960 - 1969; Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Examinations: Elementary and High School. Yiddish language, history, holidays, Bible, Yiddish literature, social issues., 1970 - 1979; Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Informational Material, Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 26, Folder 10)
    History, Philosophy, Curriculum of Yiddish Schools. All with AR/WC imprint. "Suggested Materials for School Boards and Parent Organizations." No date. English. "Program Materials for Parents' Organizations." No date. English. Joseph C. Landis, "The Relevance of Yiddish." Jewish Heritage, Fall 1969. English. Aileen Novick, "The Dying Language that Refuses to Die," Hadassah Magazine, 1967. J. Noskowitz, "Cultural Jewishness." Not date, no publication. E. S. Goldsmsith, "Yiddish in Modern Judaism," Reconstructionist, 1961. No author, "What We Stand For."
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Publications for Children. argentine beynelelkh no. 186 (1956). Monthly illustrated children's journal from Argentina. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. School and Affiliated Organization Newsletters and Bulletins. AR/WC., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 26, Folder 12)
    buleten, Jan. 1965 and Jan. 1966. Yiddish. nayes arum der shul/in and around the shule. andandx0023;1, Nov. 1965. andandx0023;1, Nov. 1966. (sic) andandx0023;2, Jan. 1966 (sic). andandx0023;2, Feb. 1967 (sic). Bronx, NY. English.
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Student Notebooks and Class Notes. AR/WC. Yiddish language notebook from AR shul, Bronx, NY. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. School Performances and Scripts from School Plays. A. Katz, gut morgn, alef. purim-shpil un yosele. No publisher: New York, 1950. B. Segal, dray kinder shpiln. Farlag Havig: Rochester, NY, 1953. Handwritten page of a purim-shpil in notebook, followed by other notes. Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. School Performances and Scripts from School Plays. Various scripts. No date. Yiddish. Leaflet for "The World of Sholem Aleichem," with Z. Mlotek. English. No date., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Outreach/Publicity Regarding Schools. WC/AR. Leaflet re AR shul 3-14, Bronx., No date.; Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Holiday Materials. WC/AR leaflet announcing model seder, AR shul 3-14, Bronx, 1975.; Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Songs: Music and Lyrics. Songsheets in Yiddish and Hebrew, with English transliteration. Mikhl Gelbart, operetes. lialkes. murashkes.. Metro Music: New York, 1949. WC/AR mimeographed booklet, lomir kinder zingen lider. Yiddish and transliteration., 1955.; Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Student Writings, Published and Unpublished [1 of 2], Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    Published pamphlet, "Essays/kinder shraybn. I.L. Peretz WC/AR Shul, Cleveland, 1962. Yiddish. Various handwritten and mimeographed sheets, Yiddish and English.
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Student Writings, Published and Unpublished [2 of 2], Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Student Writings, Published and Unpublished. Various handwritten and mimeographed sheets, Yiddish and English., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Tributes, Speeches, Anniversary Celebrations. Mimeographed pages, Yiddish and English. Graduation speech (Robin Elenko), 1977, concerning partisans/ Holocaust survivors Shimon and Khayele Palevsky. English. Typewritten commemorations of the 50th anniversary of I.L. Peretz's death (1965). Yiddish., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Secular Rituals and Life cycle Events. J. Mlotek, ed. and Education Director, WC/AR. 1971. yizker/In Memoriam. Materials for mourning from Yiddish and world literature and traditional Jewish sources., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Yiddish Camp Materials. Camp Hemshekh, 1969. English. Camp Boiberik, 1965, "felker yom tov." WC/AR mir zingen. Songbook from Camp Kinder-Ring, 1960. Transliterated English., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. School Publicity: Newspaper Clippings. NY Times, 1/16/74, about WC/AR shuln in New York., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 27, Folder 12)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Pedagogical Materials: Yiddish Literature. Single-page copies of various Yiddish stories. Yiddish and English., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 27, Folder 13)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Photographs., undated; Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 27, Folder 14)
    2 photos of WC/AR shul 3-14.
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Holiday Materials., undated; Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 27, Folder 15)
    Booklet, "What Everyone Should Know Jewish Holidays, Festivals and Fast Days." Channing Bete: Greenfield, MA, 1976. WC/AR, "Jewish Program Suggestions." Songs and readings. English and transliterated Yiddish. Songs in Yiddish and transliterated about holidays.
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Holiday Materials. Jewish People's School, Montreal., undated; Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 27, Folder 16)
    shvues. Yiddish and Hebrew. Mimeographed coloring book with poems. shabat. Same info.
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Pedagogical Materials: Holocaust. Anthology, in geto. "TVISHO and Scholem Aleijem" ("Secular Jewish Schools") Biblioteca Escolar: Buenos Aires, 1947. Yiddish. No author, "Mir zaynen do. gevenzen yidishe katzetler un partizaner." New York, 1955. Yiddish. "20 Songs of the Ghettos." Congress for Jewish Culture, New York: 1963. Yiddish and English, including musical notation. Holocaust. --Typewritten text undated, Yiddish: "dray epizodn fun iberlebungn in di lagern--dertseylt fun unzer shokhn moyshe goldshteyn." Manuscript, Yiddish, 3/29/50: "tolne zol lebn." Manuscript, Yiddish, 1/8/50: "polozh.", Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Pedagogical Materials: Israel. Booklet, Hebrew and Yiddish, "Bracha li-yom ha-atzmaut li-medinat yisrael". yidishe folksshuln/batei sefer ammiim yehudiim: Montreal, Canada, roughly 1950., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Holiday Materials: Chanukah. Chanukah. The Education Dept. of the Workmen's Circle/AR: New York, undated. English and Yiddish. Window Stencil Set for Chanukah. Shulsinger Brothers: New York, undated. Children's program, undated, Yiddish: y. goykhberg. "khanike durkhn radio." Chanukah program, undated, English. "khanike likht seremonye," undated. Khanike, "bearbet loyt y. goykhberg's 'khanike-shpil,' muzik geshribn fun malke gotlib, illustrirt fun tsirl valetsky." ufgang un shul-tsenter bam yidishn kultur-kongres in nyu-york: New York, 1967. Chanukah materials, Yiddish and English. Invitations to Chanukah celebrations in WC/AR schools, 1957., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal.Holiday Materials: Chanukah [1 of 2], Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    Chanukah celebration programs and texts, Yiddish and transliteration. Kislev. yidishe folksshuln/batei sefer ammiim yehudiim/Jewish People's Schools: Montreal, roughly 1950. Yiddish and Hebrew. "Thought for Chanukah," WC School 3-14, Bronx, NY, Dec. 1974. Children's materials in Yiddish and English. Folder with program for Hanukah performance 1978 (Yiddish handwritten) and on other side list of presenters representing moral and ethical values.
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal.Holiday Materials: Chanukah [2 of 2], Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Holiday Materials: Purim., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    "Haynt iz Purim," aroysgegebn durkh di shiler fun II-tn kurs fun lerer seminar, Pariz, 1950. Booklet, Hebrew and English: "Megillas Esther" Mesivtha Tifereth Jerusalem of America, 1976. Booklet, Yiddish and English. "Purim." WC Education Dept.: New York, 1965. "Purim." WC Education Dep't: New York, 1975. Transliterated and Yiddish-text materials for children.
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Holiday Materials: Passover., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    Chaim Raphael. The Feast of History: Hagadah shel Pesach. Steimatsky's Agency, Ltd: London and Jerusalem:1972. Martin Berkowitz. Haggadah for the American Family. Marion, PA, 1958/63.
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Holiday Materials: Passover., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    "A Third Seder," WC Education Dep't, New York, undated. "hagode shel pesakh," compiled by D. Ignatoff, Mosholu-Montefiore Community Ctr.,1963. Hagode shel peysekh. yidishe folksshuln/batei --sefer ammiim yehudiim/Jewish People's Schools: Montreal. Yiddish and Hebrew.
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Games. Lotto card game: "der lotto shpil.", Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Games. 'alef-beys' game. Leyzer Ran. kortn-leksikon:"fun eliyohu bokher biz hirsh glik." vilner farlag: New York, 1963., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Pedagogical Materials: Hebrew H. Izak. Sukat ha-Duvshanim: Sefer lfi Henzel vi-Gretel. Hotsaat Rodin: Tel Aviv, 1944. Dr. Shaul Barkali. Luah ha-Pialim ha-Shalem. Rubin Moss: Jerusalem 1953. Yehoshua ha-Parua. Hotsaat 'Taltalim': Tel Aviv. Dr. Yitzhak Peretz. Tahbir ha-Lashon ha-Ivrit. Hotsaat 'Masada' bea'm, 1952. Jehuda Halevi: Zionslieder, trans. Franz Rosenzweig. Schocken Verlag: Berlin 1933. German-Hebrew facing translation. Fragment, book of children's poetry., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Pedagogical Materials: Hebrew Prof. Shlomo Mareh-Nof ve-Eliezer Shultz. Sefer Emunim li-'ha-ivri'. Hotsaat Teuda: Chicago, 1950. David Bridger. ha-Sefer ha-Shlishi li-Mathilim. Delta: Los Angeles 1960. Yitzhak Shviger. Asher Siparti li-Yaldati. Hotsaat Yavneh: Tel Aviv, 1942. Fragment of English-language Hebrew textbook., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Pedagogical Materials: Hebrew Shimshen Dunsky. Imunei Dikduk: Helek Rishon. Book Center: Montreal, Canada, 1952. Notebook, Hebrew, by Chana Krystal (from a course, possibly taught by Dunsky)., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Krystal, Shloyme, Estate of Chana Krystal. Pedagogical Materials: Hebrew David Bridger. Ha-Sefer ha-Sheni li-Mathilim. Delta: California, 1951/1961. Idem. Ha-Sefer ha-Shlishi li-Mathilim. Delta: California, 1955. Idem. Targili, books 2-3. Delta: California, 1953, 1960., Accession no. 1997-256 (Box 29, Folder 4)